{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This politician dubbed the Smedley Butler-alleged \"Business Plot\" a \"Cocktail Putsch.\" This man's first act in office was to order the arrest of gangster \"Lucky\" Luciano, just before this man instituted a ban on the sale of artichokes. This collaborator of Robert Moses curbed the strength of Tammany Hall and was the first Italian-American to serve as mayor of a major city. A Queens airport is named for, for ten points which New York City mayor during the 1930s and '40s?",
      "answer": "Fiorello La Guardia"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country was governed by flight lieutenant Jerry Rawlings following a 1981 coup against the Convention People's Party. This country became the first colony in sub- Saharan Africa to achieve sovereignty under the regime of Kwame Nkrumah [[KWAH-meh en-KROO-muh]]. The only Black Secretary General of the United Nations, Kofi Annan [[KOH- fee ah-NAHN]], was originally from this country. The Ashanti once dominated, for ten points, what West African country ruled by Britain as the Gold Coast colony?",
      "answer": "Republic of Ghana"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's illegitimate son Don John pacified a rebellion of former Muslims in Alpujarras [[al-poo-HAH-rahs]] and led a fleet which included a young Miguel De Cervantes [[sehr-VAHN-tehs]]. This Holy Roman Emperor outlawed Martin Luther's teachings in the Diet of Worms [[VURMS]], and he deployed conquistadores like Hernán Cortés to the New World. For ten points, name this Habsburg Emperor of Spain and Austria, the father of Phillip II.",
      "answer": [
        "Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor",
        "Carlos V",
        "or Karl V",
        "Charles I of Spain",
        "or Carlos I de España",
        "or Charles II of Burgundy",
        "or Charles II de Bourgogne"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During the investigation of this event, which had many indirect links to the Elohim [[EH-loh-heem]] City compound, Michael Brescia [[BREH-shah]] was briefly detained on suspicion of being the so-called \"John Doe 2.\" Charles Porter took an iconic photograph of the aftermath of this event. The Alfred P. Murrah Federal Building was targeted in this event, for which Terry Nichols was sentenced to life in prison. For ten points, Timothy McVeigh was executed as the main perpetrator of what April 1995 act of right-wing terrorism?",
      "answer": [
        "Oklahoma City Bombing",
        "similar answers for “Bombing” such as “Attack”",
        "answers that indicate the attack on the Alfred P. Murrah Federal Building before it is mentioned 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 7"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Despite Social Democrat attempts at moderating this government, radicals such as Alfred Hugenberg [[HYOO-gen-berg]], Ernst Thalmann's Red Front, and the Brownshirts played a key role in bringing it down. In 1932, this government's presidential election saw a World War One general, Paul von Hindenburg, claim victory. This government fell after its parliament burned down, leading to the Reichstag Fire Decree. For ten points, name this democratic German government.",
      "answer": [
        "Weimar Republic or Weimarer Republik",
        "German Republic",
        "Deutsche Republik before \"German\" is mentioned",
        "\"Reich\" in place of \"Republic\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "John Hyrcanus [[heer-KAH-nooss]] subjugated and converted Itureans [[\"eye\"-TOO- ree-ans]] to this faith after a prolonged campaign. Two scholars of this faith who convinced the Himyarite [[HIM-yah-rite]] king Abu Karib to lift his siege of Yathrib later facilitated his conversion to this faith. The kingdom of Judah's fall to Nebuchadnezzar's [[NEH-boo-kahd- ZEH-zars]] forces led to a period experienced by this faith's adherents known as the Babylonian Captivity. For ten points, name this dominant faith of the Israelites.",
      "answer": [
        "Judaism",
        "Jewish Faith",
        "or Jews"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A subspecies of this animal named for the London Underground is thought to have caused a human encephalitis [[en-seh-fah-LAI-tiss]] outbreak in New York City. A \"wooden wonder\" manufactured by de Havilland and named for this animal was a high-speed light bomber used in World War Two. A Central American coastal kingdom that shares its name with this animal became a British protectorate before being annexed by Nicaragua. A major vector for historical and modern diseases like Yellow Fever and Malaria is, for ten points, what blood-sucking insect?",
      "answer": [
        "Mosquitoes",
        "Culicidae",
        "London Underground Mosquitoes",
        "Mosquito Coast"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Germany long resisted the implementation of this policy until the SPD made it the key point of coalition negotiations in 2013. A 1994 article by Alan Kreuger and David Card found that differences in this policy between New Jersey and Pennsylvania did not affect employment rates. This policy was first implemented in the U.S. by the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 and was last changed in 2007 at the federal level when it was set at $7.25. For ten points, name this lowest legally allowed rate for hourly labor compensation.",
      "answer": "Minimum wage"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Münzmeister [[MOONTS-my-stuh]] were heads of one of these facilities first established in the Carolingian [[kay-roh-LIN-jee-an]] Empire, usually coming from the burgher class. In ancient Rome, these institutions evolved from the Temples of Juno Moneta. The oldest of these buildings was likely in Lydia [[LID-ee-ah]] and produced items made from electrum. The Fugio Cent was made by the United States' first example of these institutions. Often incorporating images of rulers and presidents, for ten points, what institutions produce coins?",
      "answer": [
        "Mints",
        "Moneyers"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Wadai Sultanate annexed a kingdom southeast of this body of water which was ruled by \"Mbang\" kings and was called Bagirmi. Ibn Furtu chronicled the military exploits of a Mai of an empire near this body of water named Idris Alooma. This lake shares its name with a country which with Libya fought the Toyota War over the Aouzu Strip. This lake in the Sahel has shrunk by 95% since 1960. For ten points, identify this lake that names a country governed from N’Djamena [[uhn-jah-MAY-nuh]].",
      "answer": "Lake Chad 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 7"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This modern country was the heartland of the medieval Mutapa Empire. This country's predecessor state was governed briefly by Bishop Muzorewa [[moo-zoh-REH- wah]] following the Lancaster House Agreement. A \"Bush War\" in this country ended with the rise of the ZANU-PF and its leader Robert Mugabe. Mugabe's thirty-year presidency occurred in, for ten points, what southeast African country that succeeded Rhodesia?",
        "answer": [
          "Republic of Zimbabwe",
          "Republic of Rhodesia",
          "Southern Rhodesia until mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Rhodesia was named for Cecil Rhodes, a British politician who, through his company De Beers, established a monopoly on this good.",
        "answer": "Diamonds"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Supported by Guadalupe Victoria, this figure rose in rebellion against Emperor Augustin I [[ow-goo-STEEN the first]] in the Casa Mata Plan Revolution. This perpetrator of the Goliad Massacre gave a full military burial to his leg after it was hit by cannon fire during the Pastry War. This man captured the former mission-turned-fort of the Alamo during the War of Texan Independence. For ten points, name this Mexican general and president who resisted an 1840s invasion of his nation by the Polk administration.",
        "answer": [
          "Antonio López de Santa Anna",
          "Antonio de Padua María Severino López de Santa Anna y Pérez de Lebrón"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Santa Anna fought this inconclusive battle against Zachary Taylor at La Angostura. Once news of this battle made it to the United States, it was hailed as a great victory.",
        "answer": "Battle of Buena Vista"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man bucked the trends of post-Civil War historiography in his book Black Reconstruction in America. This thinker, who publicly debated white supremacist Lothrop Stoddard, was the founding editor of the magazine The Crisis. This man believed that full civil rights would be accomplished through the efforts of a group he dubbed the \"Talented Tenth.\" For ten points, name this American-Ghanaian sociologist who wrote The Souls of Black Folk.",
        "answer": "W. E. B. Du Bois ] or William Edward Burghardt Du Bois"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Crisis is the official magazine of what civil rights organization, co-founded by Du Bois, which refused to issue a public statement of support during his investigation by the FBI, leading to Du Bois's estrangement?",
        "answer": "NAACP or the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 7"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Union control was solidified in this U.S. state after Don Carlos Buell's strategic victory at the Battle of Perryville. According to President Lincoln, losing this state was \"nearly the same as to lose the whole game.\" This state's city of Paducah was raided in 1864 by Confederate general Nathan Bedford Forrest. Though neither man represented this state, it was the birthplace of both Jefferson Davis and Abraham Lincoln. For ten points, name this border state during the U.S. Civil War.",
        "answer": "Kentucky"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Kentucky native was James Buchanan's vice president, the youngest ever, and was nominated by the Southern Democrats to run in the hotly-contested Election of 1860.",
        "answer": "John Cabell Breckinridge"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The ancient city of Zadracarta sat on this body of water and was the seat of power of Hyrcania. This body of water marked the western extent of the Chinese Empire during the Tang Dynasty, and it was primarily explored by Fedor Soimonov [[SOY-mon-off]] during the reign of Peter the Great. The city of Derbent, which lies on this body of water, was handed over in the Treaty of Gulistan from Persia to Russia. For ten points, name this largest inland body of water, named for an ancient Caucasian tribe.",
        "answer": [
          "Caspian Sea",
          "Mazandaran Sea",
          "or Hyrcania Sea",
          "or Khazar Sea",
          "Kaspiyskoye more",
          "Hazar denizi"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This central Asian country, which was governed for nearly three decades by Nursultan Nazarbayev [[nah-zar-BYE-yev]], lies northeast of the Caspian Sea and has the longest coastline of any country on it.",
        "answer": "Republic of Kazakhstan or Qazaqstan Respublikasy"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The oldest-known evidence of this kind of event was found on a three thousand- year old Japanese skeleton discovered in 2021. A number of these incidents occurred on the Jersey Shore in 1916, and, after being torpedoed by the Japanese in 1945, the survivors of the USS Indianapolis dealt with hundreds of these incidents while waiting for rescue. For ten points, name these historically-feared events in which a large cartilaginous [[kar-tih-LAH- jih-nus]] fish injures or kills a human.",
        "answer": [
          "Shark attack or Shark bite",
          "descriptive answers involving humans being attacked and/or injured by sharks"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the past decade, the waters off which U.S. East Coast landmass have been the site of extremely dense white shark concentrations, leading to five attacks since 2012? Bartholemew Gosnold led the first English expedition to this landmass and coined its name in 1602.",
        "answer": "Cape Cod 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 7"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This author created Sylvia Gellburg, a Jewish woman who falls victim to psychosomatic paralysis after reading an article about Kristallnacht. The outing of this writer's Communist sympathies by his former friend Elia Kazan to the House Un-American Activities Committee was parodied in his play, A View from the Bridge. Joe Keller knowingly ships defective aircraft parts during the Second World War in this author's play All My Sons. The author of The Crucible was, for ten points, which mid-20th century playwright?",
        "answer": "Arthur Miller or Arthur Asher Miller"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Miller's most famous spouse was which film icon who was known for playing comedic blondes in films like Some Like It Hot and The Seven Year Itch?",
        "answer": "Marilyn Monroe or Norma Jeane Mortenson"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "\"Dynamic cubist\" Jacob Lawrence painted a 60-panel series about this event, which is the subject of Isabel Wilkerson's The Warmth of Other Suns. Chester Burnett and Muddy Waters moved to Chicago during this event, which presaged the Harlem Renaissance. For ten points, name this major demographic shift in the mid-twentieth century United States, in which millions of African Americans moved out of the South.",
        "answer": [
          "Great Migration",
          "Great Northward Migration",
          "or Black Migration",
          "Migration Series",
          "or The Migration of the Negro"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What American author depicted the Black communities of the industrial North following the Great Migration in her novels The Bluest Eye and Song of Solomon?",
        "answer": [
          "Toni Morrison",
          "Chloe Anthony Wofford Morrison",
          "or Chloe Ardelia Wofford"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Duels",
      "prompt": "Concerning dueling in American history, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Secretary of the Treasury who was killed in a duel by Aaron Burr.",
          "answer": "Alexander Hamilton"
        },
        {
          "question": "President, nicknamed “Old Hickory,” who killed Charles Dickinson in a duel.",
          "answer": "Andrew Jackson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who crossed swords with Illinois politician James Shields before becoming the first Republican president in 1860.",
          "answer": "Abraham Lincoln"
        },
        {
          "question": "Hero of the Barbary Wars who was shot and killed in a duel by James Barron.",
          "answer": "Stephen Decatur Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Boarding stable at which Wyatt Earp and Doc Holiday shot a group of Cowboys led by the Clanton brothers.",
          "answer": [
            "O.K. Corral",
            "Gunfight at the O.K. Corral",
            "equivalents"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Dangerous Kansas cattle town where numerous duels occurred, inspiring the phrase \"Get out of [this city].\"",
          "answer": "Dodge City"
        },
        {
          "question": "Folk hero and gunslinger who was shot and killed playing poker in Deadwood.",
          "answer": [
            "Wild Bill Hickock",
            "either underlined answer"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Revolutionary War general who was shot by John Laurens in a duel after disrespecting George Washington.",
          "answer": "Charles Henry Lee 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 7"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Nero",
      "prompt": "Concerning Roman Emperor Nero, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Island annexed during his reign, the site of Boudicca's Revolt, which sacked Londinium.",
          "answer": [
            "Great Britain",
            "Britannia",
            "Albion"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Religious group Nero used as a scapegoat for the Great Fire of Rome, according to Tacitus.",
          "answer": [
            "Christianity or Christians",
            "Catholics"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Number of emperors in the Year 69 who succeeded Nero, ending with Vespasian.",
          "answer": [
            "Four",
            "Year of the Four Emperors"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Historiographical term for the first dynasty of Roman emperors which died out following Nero's death.",
          "answer": "Julio-Claudian Dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mother of Nero whom he tried to kill via poison and a collapsible boat.",
          "answer": "Agrippina the Younger"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tutor of Nero and stoic philosopher who killed himself once he was implicated in the Pisonian Conspiracy.",
          "answer": "Seneca the Younger or Lucius Annaeus Seneca the Younger"
        },
        {
          "question": "Freedman who killed Nero, put to death twenty years later by Domitian for that crime.",
          "answer": "Tiberius Claudius Epaphroditus ]"
        },
        {
          "question": "Phrase said by Nero's mother shortly before her assassination, cursing Nero for being her child.",
          "answer": [
            "\"Smite my Womb\"",
            "Ventrem feri"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 7",
      "prompt": "Concerning Indian independence, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Leader known as \"Mahatma.\"",
          "answer": "Mahatma Gandhi or Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi"
        },
        {
          "question": "First prime minister of independent India.",
          "answer": "Jawaharlal Nehru or Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru"
        },
        {
          "question": "General term for the 1947 division which separated the British Raj into Pakistan and India.",
          "answer": "Partition of India"
        },
        {
          "question": "All-India Muslim League leader who headed the independent government of Pakistan.",
          "answer": "Muhammad Ali Jinnah or Mahomedali Jinnahbhai"
        },
        {
          "question": "1930 \"March\" sometimes known as the \"Satyagraha [[sah-tyah-GRAH-hah]].\"",
          "answer": [
            "Salt march to Dandi",
            "the Dandi March"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Last British Governor-General of India who oversaw official independence.",
          "answer": "Lord Mountbatten or Louis Mountbatten, 1st Earl Mountbatten of Burma"
        },
        {
          "question": "Hindu term for \"self-governance,\" used synonymously with \"home-rule.\"",
          "answer": "Swaraj ]"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of the INA who made overtures to the Axis powers in an attempt to free the subcontinent from British rule.",
          "answer": [
            "Subhas Chandra Bose",
            "Netaji 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 7"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this election year, volunteers were encouraged to “go clean for Gene” while supporting Eugene McCarthy in the New Hampshire primary. Curtis LeMay earned controversy for suggesting the use of (20 pts)",
        "nuclear weapons in this year as the vice- presidential nominee for George Wallace’s third-party run. Richard Daley was accused of using “Gestapo (10 pts)",
        "Tactics” at this year’s DNC in Chicago, which nominated Hubert Humphrey. For ten points, name this election year when Richard Nixon won his first term in office."
      ],
      "answer": "1968"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Several powers in this conflict were criticized in the pamphlet The Conduct of the Allies. A 70-day siege of Tournai [[toor-NAY]] occurred during this conflict, in which one side lost over 10,000 men in a victory over the Duke of Villars. A monopoly over the (20 pts)",
        "slave trade was given to England in the treaty ending this conflict. A battle in this war led to a number of poems written to celebrate the Duke of (10 pts)",
        "Marlborough. For ten points, name this Europe-wide conflict in which the Battle of Blenheim [[BLEN-em]] was fought."
      ],
      "answer": "War of the Spanish Succession"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Historian Walter LaFeber [[lah-FEE-ber]] wrote that U.S. intervention in this overseas conflict marked “the origins of modern presidential powers.” Five thousand troops from the U.S. were sent by President McKinley to quell this rebellion sometimes called the (20 pts)",
        "Yìhétuán [[YEE-HEH-TWAHN]] Movement. This armed conflict arose from increasing tensions between foreign missionaries and (10 pts)",
        "Chinese rebels. For ten points, name this late 19th-century Chinese rebellion led by the Righteous and Harmonious Fists."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Boxer Rebellion or Boxer Uprising",
        "Yìhétuán Movement",
        "Yìhétuán yùndòng before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An Aristophanes [[ah-reh-STOH-fah-nees]] play titled for this occupation included a competition of who can be more shameless between a sausage seller and an analogue of the politician Creon. Arcite [[ahr-SEE-teh]] and Palamon are (20 pts)",
        "two soldiers imprisoned in a tower by Theseus and fall in love with his sister-in-law Emelye [[\"Emily\"]] in a \"Tale\" (10 pts)",
        "named for this profession. In one story, Gawain battles a \"Green\" one of these people. For ten points, name this medieval chivalric class of warriors."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Knights",
        "The Knights",
        "Knight's Tale",
        "Hippeis"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While proconsul of Cilicia [[sih-LIH-shuh]], this man marched two battered legions to relieve the siege of fellow governor Cassius from a Parthian siege at Antioch. Publius Clodius Pulcher [[POOL-care]] directly targeted this politician by passing a law to exile any public official who (20 pts)",
        "executed a Roman citizen without trial. This man, who put down the Cataline Conspiracy, later refused to join the (10 pts)",
        "First Triumvirate. For ten points, name this Roman orator of the 1st century B.C."
      ],
      "answer": "Marcus Tullius Cicero"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A bank connected to this man run by Roberto Calvi faced controversy after it funneled money to both sides of the Nicaraguan Civil War. This figure narrowly escaped the Nazi Black Sunday roundup of youth after the Warsaw (20 pts)",
        "Ghetto uprising, hiding in his uncle’s basement in Krakow. Grey Wolves member Mehmet Ali Agca [[AHD-juh]] fired and injured this (10 pts)",
        "holy figure in St. Peter’s Square. For ten points, name this Polish Pope who was succeeded by Benedict XVI [[the sixteenth]]."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Pope John Paul II or Ioannes Paulus II",
        "Karol Józef Wojtyła"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was born in the Wallowa [[wall-OW-ah]] Valley with a name meaning \"Thunder Rolling Down the Mountain.\" This man’s heart was “sick and sad” in 1877 after he failed to escape into (20 pts)",
        "Canada and was forced to surrender to U.S. soldiers led by Nelson Miles. This man was a leader of a tribe that is often known by a two-word (10 pts)",
        "French phrase meaning “pierced nose.” For ten points, name this Nez Percé [[NEZ \"PURSE\"]] chief who vowed “I will fight no more forever.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Chief Joseph"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Because of this man’s system of natural philosophy, Gisbert Voetius [[GIZ- behrt VEE-tee-ooss]] persuaded the University of Utrecht [[YOO-trekt]] to condemn this man, who retaliated with the publication of Comments on a Certain Broadsheet. Using the (20 pts)",
        "“Wax Example,” this man theorized that things are perceived through our intellect, and he believed deductive reasoning proved God’s (10 pts)",
        "existence. This man developed a system to plot points on a namesake plane. For ten points, name this French mathematician and philosopher whose views are best exemplified by his quote, “I think therefore I am.”"
      ],
      "answer": "René Descartes ] or Renatus Cartesius"
    }
  ]
}